# Ivan Alles

# Machine Learning Software Engineer

<u>ivan.alles@gmail.com</u> +49 176 2378 3872 qithub.com/ivan-alles linkedin.com/in/ivanalles voutube portfolio

I'm a software engineer focusing on machine learning, computer robot vision, and robotics with 25+ years of software development experience. As an early Al adopter, I've accomplished 10+ deep learning projects for industrial tasks.

# Skills

Expert: Python, C++, C, numpy, OpenCV, CNTK, SVN.

Advanced: TensorFlow, C#, .NET, algorithms, robotics, SQL, Point Cloud Library, Git.

Familiar: TensorFlow.js, music information retrieval, Javascript, Vue, pandas, Java, Qt, Perl,

Pascal, UML, OpenGL.

# Work History

# **User-friendly AI framework for Industry**

Founder at Urobots, 2019-2021

- Leading a team of experts, created a user-friendly AI framework to solve computer vision and robotics problems without coding.
- Developed AI algorithms for classification, object detection, semantic segmentation, robot-camera calibration.
- Designed REST APIs.
- Implemented software modules for camera, robot, and advanced Blockly programming.
- Applied the framework in 10+ customer projects.

Python, TensorFlow, CNTK, OpenCV.

# <u>Demonstration of human-Al collaboration in computational creativity</u> (hobby project)

Software engineer, 2018-2021

- Developed a model to learn user preferences.
- Optimized GAN generator for usage in javascript.
- Developed a web application demonstrating human-Al collaboration in computational creativity.

Python, TensorFlow, TensorFlow.js, javascript, Vue.

# **Neural Network for Object Detection for industrial projects**

Founder at Urobots, 2019-2021

- Developed computer vision algorithms for real-time object localization, achieving accuracy < 2 pix in position and < 2° in rotation.
- Created a transfer learning model, reducing the required number of training data by 90%.
- Applied the algorithm in 10+ projects in robotics, object counting, quality assurance. Python, TensorFlow, TensorFlow.js, OpenCV, javascript, Vue.

# **Embedded AI** for IDS Imaging

Founder at Urobots, 2019-2021

- Pioneered the introduction of deep learning models in low-energy consumption environments (CPU, FPGA).
- Applied deep learning in an <u>interactive exhibit</u> in Germany's most prominent science center.

Python, TensorFlow, CNTK, OpenCV, ARM, FPGA, Linux.

## Robot vision to grasp unknown objects for Cronimet

Founder at Urobots, 2016-2019

- Implemented algorithms for segmentation and grasping of previously unseen objects in 2D and 3D.
- Designed and developed software processing 3D camera input and controlling the robot. Python, TensorFlow, CNTK, OpenCV, Qt.

# Optical quality control of industrial components

Founder at Urobots, 2016-2020

- Developed methods for defect detection using the minimal "defect / no defect" input on the whole image rather than labeling each defect separately.
- Implemented software for optical quality control of industrial components: object presence, segmentation, tracking, counting.

Python, TensorFlow, CNTK, OpenCV, Qt.

# Optical assembly inspection of plate heat exchangers for Mahle

Founder at Urobots, 2012-2021

- Developed algorithms and applications to check the assembly correctness of products consisting of hundreds of near-identical specular parts, achieving 99.95% accuracy.
- Managed a team adapting the core algorithms for 100+ product types.
- Designed the relevant hardware (lightlng, cameras) for 15+ installations.

C++, python, JSON, XML, boost, OpenCV, Qt, MFC, Visual Studio.

# **Head Pose Tracking (hobby project)**

Software engineer, 2012

• Developed and evaluated algorithms for real-time head pose tracking in video.

C++, opency, OpenGL.

# **Computer Poker (hobby project)**

Software engineer, 2010-2012

- Developed efficient algorithms and software for the Annual Computer Poker Competition.
- The program reached 4th place in the limit hold 'em 2-player event, challenging teams with tenfold human, computer, and time resources.

C#, C++, Java, Maven, Linux.

# **Automated Baggage Loading System for Grenzebach**

Freelance software engineer, 2009-2013

- Developed methods and software for 3D object recognition and registration.
- Developed methods and software for LIDARs-robot calibration, reducing manual effort by 90%.
- Implemented physics and LIDAR simulation.
- Developed algorithms for optimization of container loading (3D knapsack).
- Designed and implemented production software and tools.

C++, XML, MFC, boost, Point Cloud Library.

#### Automotive drivers and middleware for SMSC

Freelance software engineer, 2007-2012

- Designed and developed various drivers: QNX Sound, Media Local Bus, EEPROM, Timer, GPIO.
- Implemented MOST middleware.
- Implemented PC simulation.

C, C++, C#, Visual Studio, Windows CE, ARM, INIC, Linux, QNX, OSEK.

# **GUI Coverage Profiler (hobby project)**

Software engineer, 2007-2008

- Developed instrumentation methods required working on .NET assemblies without access to the source code.
- Designed and implemented a program for measuring test coverage of GUI elements in .NET applications.

C#, C++, Visual Studio, Linux.

# C++ refactoring tool (hobby project)

Software engineer, 2007

- Developed scripts to convert the C++ grammar to the intermediate language of GNU tools Flex and Bison.
- Implemented a syntax error-tolerant parser and semantic analyzer.
- Programmed an add-in for Visual Studio to make code refactoring using a context menu.

C++, C#, perl, boost, Visual Studio.

## **Automotive drivers for Harman Becker Automotive Systems**

Freelance software engineer, 2006-2007

- Replaced a hardware parallel bus with a software-based serial bus, reducing hardware costs by 10% and CPU load by 90%.
- Designed and implemented peripheral device drivers (SPI, RS-232, MLB, I2C) with CPU load reduced by 90% due to the use of DMA.
- Managed a team developing a boot loader for a radio unit.

C, C++, Visual Studio, V850, OSEK, INIC.

# **Control module for chemical analysis for Agilent Technologies**

Software engineer at K2L GmbH, 2002-2005

- Implemented software components: GUI, generic data processing, inter-processor communication, device drivers.
- Designed and implemented a visual form editor for GUI development, simulation, and test tools.

C++, XML, Visual Studio, MFC, wxWidgets, Motorola MPC5200, OSE.

#### Automotive software and tools for German car manufacturers

Software engineer at K2L GmbH, 2000-2005

- Designed and developed GUI for instrument panels for Audi, VW, and Iveco.
- Designed and implemented the MOST Network Master function block for BMW. The software was 100% compliant with the MOST specification and became a reference project for ISO 9001 certification.
- Managed a team implementing device drivers (USB, RS-232) and tools.

C++, C, XML, Visual Studio, ARM7, ST10, Windows CE, OSEK.

## **Backend software for internet applications for E-Commerce**

Software developer at Actis Systems Internet, 1999-2000

- Designed and implemented an application for monitoring changes in websites.
- Developed backend database management tools.

C++, COM, MS SQL Server, Oracle.

## Photoscan for Science Center of Komi Republic, Russia

Freelance software engineer, 1999

- Developed methods and software to measure the volume of round timber on camera images.
- Managed the development team.

C++, image processing.

#### In-house software development for Energosbyt

Software Engineer at Energosbyt, 1998-1999

- Designed a contractors' database, incorporating contractors of all subsidiaries of the company.
- Designed and implemented a program for analyzing customers' data.
- Maintained and enhanced the company's software, consulted over 50 users.

Visual Basic, Fox Pro.

# In-house software development for Komi Bank of Sberbank of Russia

Software Engineer at Komi Bank of Sberbank of Russia, 1996-1998

- Designed and implemented an analytical information system, incorporating financial indexes, information about all bank transactions, and a collection of converters for importing data from various sources.
- This work was awarded the First Prize in the "Young Banker 1997" republican competition.

Visual Basic, MS Access.

# **Electronic Signature for Bank Evropeysky Sever**

Software developer at Diploma project, 1994-1995

• Developed an algorithm and implemented software to compress scanned signatures to 1% of the original size.

C++, Borland, image processing.

# Education

# Master of Science (M.S.) in Applied Mathematics

Syktyvkar State University, Russia 1990 – 1995

# Courses

#### **Music Information Retrieval**

University of Victoria, 2021

Studied <u>Extracting Information From Music Signals</u>, Machine Learning for Music Information Retrieval, Music Retrieval Systems.

#### **Robotics**

Columbia University, 2017

Core techniques for representing robots that perform physical tasks in the real world.

#### **Machine Learning**

Stanford University, 2016

Certificate in machine learning.

## **Machine Learning Foundations**

University of Washington, 2016

Studied classification, regression, and practical applications of machine learning.

# Languages

Fluent in English, German, and Russian (native language). Elementary proficiency in Chinese.

# Hobbies

Hiking, cross-country skiing, yoga, computer games.